All right, חברה chevre בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is
ק''ז kuf zayin 107. We are quickly coming in for a landing
here. All right, we pick up at the very bottom of ק''ו
עמוד ב' kuf vav amud bet and we are dealing with the
משנה mishna about the שני דייני גזירות shnei dayanei gezerot and אדמון,
Admon, and one of the things the first אדמון Admon said was
the case about somebody who went למדינת הים, limdinat hayam, this is
what he's doing in this מסכת. masechet. Somebody who went overseas and
his wife needs food and he says that she takes an oath
at the end and not at the beginning, and the בני כהנים
גדולים bnei kohanim gedolim said at the beginning and the end. Not
exactly clear what the beginning and the end is. End is presumably
when it comes time to finally collect the full כתובה ksuva if
he winds up dying, then she'll take an oath that presumably nothing
had been prepaid and that her collecting of the מזונות mezonot was
done properly, whereas the בני כהנים גדולים bnei kohanim gedolim wanted to
take an oath at the beginning to make sure that before she
starts collecting from the estate she actually deserves this money.
But of course אדמון'ס Admon's concern is that there seems to be
like a more of an immediate need to make sure that she
is provided for and do you want to sort of hold that
up or do you want to, you know, in terms of the
שבועה shvua do you want to take care of that later? So
the גמרא gemara never really fully spells out what the issues are
between the debate, but we come and take a look here at
the גמרא gemara starts with the debate of רב Rav and שמואל
Shmuel which will sort of help us frame what's going on in
that case with אדמון. Admon. So let's take a look at the
bottom of ק''ו עמוד ב'. kuf vav amud bet. מי שהלך למדינת
הים. Mi shehalach limdinat hayam. איתמר, Itmar, it was said. רב אמר,
Rav amar, רב Rav says top of ק''ז עמוד א'. kuf zayin
amud alef.
פוסקין מזונות לאשת איש. Poskin mezonot leishet ish. It seems to be
exactly the case that אדמון'ס Admon's talking about, which obviously we'll get
to אדמון Admon in a minute. That if a husband has left,
he's overseas, and the woman needs to put food on the table,
בית דין beit din goes ahead and figures out, yeah, give her
an allowance, exactly. רש''י, Rashi, בית דין יורדין לנכסי מי שהלך למדינת
הים ופוסקין מזונות לאשתו. beit din yordin lenichsei mi shehalach limdinat hayam
uposkin mezonot leishto. They take his property and sell off his property
in order to provide for his wife because he obviously has a
כתובה ksuva obligation to provide for his wife. שמואל אמר—could Shmuel amar
she
use her own money then get reimbursed later?
Well that would be another alternative, but you know then she has
to put out the funds herself and she might not have those
funds etc. Right, right, I know but שמואל'ס Shmuel's the opposite right?
Yeah. ושמואל אמר אין פוסקין מזונות לאשת איש. VeShmuel amar ein poskin
mezonot leishet ish. No, you don't do that. There are too many
things you might not know about and we'll take a look in
the גמרא gemara why שמואל Shmuel says not to do that. אמר
שמואל Amar Shmuel מודה לי אבא, modeh li Abba, אבא Abba which
is a way of referring to רב. Rav. רב Rav
would concede to me, at least שמואל'ס Shmuel's saying רב Rav would
concede to him, בשלושה חדשים הראשונים. bishlosha chadashim harishonim. The first three
months that you do not start taking from the property and selling
it off. Why? לפי שאין אדם מניח ביתו ריקם. Lefi she'ein adam
maniach beito reikam. Because we don't assume that somebody is so irresponsible
to not have set aside any money for his wife and full
provisions. So this is already signaling why שמואל Shmuel might feel in
general you do not seize the property. On the one hand it's
true there is this ongoing obligation, on the other hand what do
we know about what the arrangement was that was made? All we
know is that she's telling us that she doesn't have any food
or any money provided for her. So שמואל Shmuel wants to say
that at least רב Rav would at least concede that the first
three months that should be true, that we should give people, at
least the husbands, the benefit of the doubt for those first three
months.
Again, not very, if that's not the case she's a little bit
stuck. Maybe you know as Michael said she can borrow money and
buy and have it as an IOU and then at least, you
know, or lay out the money and then maybe get reimbursed, but
it does put her in a bit of a difficult situation. But
that's already signaling why שמואל Shmuel would say we do not do
it, because we don't really know what the setup might be and
maybe we give him to some degree a benefit of a doubt.
So let's take a look. Now the גמרא'ס gemara's going to spell
out what exactly are the concerns according to שמואל. Shmuel. So the
גמרא gemara says like this: וכששמעו בו שמת כולי עלמא לא פליגי.
ukesheshamu bo shemet kulei alma lo pligi.
If we heard the guy died, then nobody disagrees. He's dead. This
woman has a right to be supported by the estate, right, as
long as she's not collecting her lump sum כתובה, ksuva, so everybody
agrees, you know, she gets supported by the estate then we basically
go out and provide for her. Okay, so what's the issue? The
issue is כי פליגי בשלא שמעו בו שמת. ki pligi beshelo shamu
bo shemet. You have not heard that he has died, he's just
not around. רב אמר פוסקין דמשועבד לה. Rav amar poskin dameshuba'ad lah.
Okay, so you provide for her, he's obligated to provide for her,
he's not physically around, she's telling us she doesn't have food, so
you do what you need to do. ושמואל אמר אין פוסקין. VeShmuel
amar ein poskin. You don't provide for. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's
the reason? וחד אמר—so Vechad amar now there are two explanations of
שמואל. Shmuel. וחד אמר אימא צרורי אתפסה, vechad amar emma tzerorei atfsa,
maybe צרורי tzerorei is like צרורות, tzerorot, you
know, like bundles, maybe like a bundle of money. Could be that
he already set aside money for her. So how do we know
what he did? He's not here, but, you know, but maybe he
put some money in a— a bank account for her to pay
for the מזונות. mezonot. So who are we to go ahead and
seize his property? Okay. רב פפא אמר Rav Pappa amar חיישינן שמא
אמר לה chaishinan shema amar lah צאי מעשי ידיך במזונותיך. tzei ma'aseh
yadayich bimzonotayich. Now,
there's another possibility. Maybe he said to her the time I'm not
around, your labor does not have to go for the household, you
could any labor that you do, any work that you do will
go for provide for paying for your own food bill. Now,
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both discuss the issue about whether he's
allowed to say that unilaterally or whether she has to agree. You
might remember some of that had to do with the questions about
in whose interest these laws were made, you know, the exchange of
her מעשי ידיים ma'aseh yadayim for the food. Was it made basically
to protect his interest, was it made to protect her interest? So
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both claim, although it doesn't sound that
way from the גמרא Gemara I must tell you, that it's a
case where he had said that and she had agreed to it,
that she wouldn't have needed to have agreed to it. Okay, but
that's possible. So basically what both of them are saying is we
don't know what arrangements they made. Maybe he set aside money, maybe
they agreed she would work for herself during that time. So therefore
we cannot go ahead and seize his property because there's too many
other possibilities that might be around.
If she went to בית דין Beit Din and requested money, then
they would take it. That's the case. Right, so why not just
say, so take a שבועה shvua and any of these other things
are operative.
Well, the question is, okay, so that's a good question like why
wouldn't a שבועה shvua work? You know, the question is, is does
a שבועה shvua always, like when we say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה.
hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya. You say I owe you a hundred dollars,
I say, you know, you say I owe you a hundred dollars,
I say I don't. We don't say, well why don't you just
take a שבועה shvua and then you'll be believed, because, you know,
if there's a burden of proof, there's a burden of proof. Now
here, it's not that the husband is actually saying something explicitly, we
don't know, we're in doubt. So it's not, it is possible that
you could suggest, and maybe that's actually what's going on with אדמון
Admon and
the כהנים Kohanim is that maybe a שבועה shvua will help clarify.
But it seems like let's see how that plays out, it's a
good question. It seems though that the concern is that that's a
serious enough concern that we're not prepared to assume that that doubt
will be resolved, you know, by the שבועה shvua and that's enough
to actually seize somebody's property. Although interestingly we do know that there's
a debt, but we don't know how that debt has been dealt
with. Now the other question, and maybe this will help clarify it
is, why do they not disagree after he died? Maybe even after
he died, he had pre-, you know, he had set aside the
money, he had, you know, he had set aside money to provide
for her and she has some money in a bank account. So
רש"י Rashi says those scenarios are not really concerns after he's dead.
The possibility that they made an arrangement, צאי מעשי ידיך במזונותיך, tzei
ma'aseh yadayich bimzonotayich, is not an arrangement that would apply to the
heirs, right? Even if the husband when he was alive said to
the wife, I'm not going to pay for your food bill, you
keep your own labor, once he's dead, the the estate has to
provide for her. And if she wants to have a similar arrangement
with the heirs or they want to have a similar arrangement with
her, we're not going to provide your food but you keep your
own labor, then that would have to basically be contracted new. Okay,
so therefore, that's not a relevant concern because whatever he said when
he was alive wouldn't be relevant when he's dead. How about the
possibility that he had prepaid the money? So the possibility that he
had prepaid the money, תוספות, Tosafot, רש"י Rashi says, well look, when
you come to collect your כתובה, ketubah, you're going to have to
make a שבועה shvua and there you go about the שבועה, shvua,
you're going to have to make a שבועה shvua that you haven't
pre-collected or whatever, so that's sort of covered there. So that's why
they don't debate. Of course that does raise זאב's Zev question which
is, okay, then have her make a שבועה shvua here to solve
that problem. Anyway, that's what רש"י Rashi says. תוספות Tosafot says the
reason it's not an issue once he died, and this may be
also partly just תוספות's Tosafot point, and it goes back to the
גמרא Gemara about אין אדם מניח ביתו ריקן, ein adam maniach beito
reikan, is תוספות Tosafot says no. Part of the reason we assume
some other arrangement was made was because we assume nobody would be
so dastardly to leave their wives without having made some arrangement. So
therefore, that's true if the guy is alive and is and is
somewhere else, is off in מדינת הים. medinat hayam. That gives us
a presumption that, you know, that he obviously had made some he
must have made some arrangement. Nobody would have just abandoned his household
without making an arrangement. Okay, but if he actually died, then, you
know, people do die, right? Without making arrangements, and we don't know
what the story is, and therefore we cannot go ahead and assume
that this, you know, that something has been made. Okay, so that's
anyway ways of understanding why it's different when he actually is dead
and why also שמואל Shmuel is presumed to assume that something it's
been taken care of.
If the rumor was that she got divorced, then maybe it's a
little bit different then.
Right. So we'll take a look. That's going to come up in
the גמרא. Gemara. So let's take a look.
I'm very impressed by the way. Hm? With the word dastardly. Dastardly?
Okay, anyway.
Right.
Okay. So the verse says like
this, אביי. Abaye. What difference does it make which of these reasons
you give according to שמואל? Shmuel? איכא בינייהו, Ika Beinayhu, the difference
is גדולה ולא ספקה, Gedola v'lo safka, she's an adult but she
does not earn enough money to put food on the table. Either
she has no real skills or רש"י Rashi says it's a time
of famine and food is very expensive. So that's one scenario. אינמי,
Inami, or קטנה וספקה, ktana v'safka, she's a minor and she does
have skills to earn money to put food on the table. So
what does that mean? If your concern is that he set aside
money for her, צרורי, tzerori, so the assumption is that he would
only do that if his wife was an adult, that she could
actually take possession of that money and she could be responsible, put
over a bank account in her name. As a minor, there would
not be a scenario of צרורי. tzerori. So if the issue is
about צרורי tzerori and she's a minor, then excuse me, that's if
that's why he's assumed to have made arrangements, then in the case
of a minor, that would not be a he would not have
a presumption of having made that arrangement. Okay. But if she even
as a minor she can earn her own keep, then we still
would be concerned that he made the arrangement that you'll earn your
own keep. Or the reverse, she's an adult but she can't earn
her own keep. So if there's a concern about צרורי, tzerori, about
having set up a bank account for her, that is a concern
by an adult and therefore she's not allowed we would not give
her מזונות. mezonot. We would assume he made the arrangement of a
bank account. But if the concern is is that he made the
arrangement of you'll earn your own keep and she does not have
the skills or food is so expensive that she can't earn her
own keep, then that would not be a legitimate possibility and therefore
she would be entitled to get to take the property and to
sell it to be fed. Okay, so those are the different explanations
about whether we what we will do if the guy is not
around. Now let's see how it plays out in our משנה. mishnah.
תנן, Tnan, we learn in our משנה. mishnah. מי שהלך למדינת הים,
Mi she-halach l'medinat hayam, guy went
overseas, ואשתו תובעת מזונות, v'ishto tova'at mezonot, and his wife says I
need to be fed. חנן אומר, Chanan omer, חנן Chanan says תשבע
בסוף, tishava basof, find take an oath at the end of the
process, maybe when he returns or when it's time to collect your
כתובה, ketubah, ולא תשבע בתחילה, v'lo tishava batchila, not in the beginning.
נחלקו עליו בני כהנים גדולים, Nechlaku alei bnei kohanim gedolim, the sons
of the כהנים גדולים kohanim gedolim get in, interesting that that's like
a group, and they said ואמרו תשבע בתחילה ובסוף, v'amru tishava batchila
u'basof,
beginning and at the end. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: עד כאן לא פליגי אלא לענין שבועה. ad kan lo pligi
ela inyan shevu'ah. What they're debating is when you make the שבועה.
shevu'ah. אבל מזוני יהבינן לה, aval mezonei yahvinan lah,
but we do give her מזונות. mezonot. And שמואל Shmuel says we
do not give her מזונות. mezonot. And here Dove, this without saying
why, but it explicitly addresses your case. The גמרא Gemara is not
going to say oh well with the שבועה shevu'ah שמואל Shmuel would
agree. No, שמואל Shmuel feels that for whatever reason a שבועה shevu'ah
won't be enough. We will not give her מזונות mezonot regardless. And
here you are giving her מזונות. mezonot. What's the explanation? So the
גמרא Gemara says: תרגמה שמואל, Targama Shmuel, so שמואל Shmuel interpreted it,
בששמעו בו שמת. b'she'shamu bo shemet.
It's a case where he's not actually alive or presumed to be
alive. He's presumed to be dead and she wants to be supported
in terms of the support she gets from the estate as a
widow. Okay. Now of course what's so funny about that is is
that what does it have to do with מי שהלך למדינת הים?
mi she-halach l'medinat hayam? Right? It's a very weak answer because then
it should have just said מי שמת ואשתו תובעת מזונות. mi she-met
v'ishto tova'at mezonot.
Right. Right. You know it's basically he's just dead. Right. And I
mean we'll see in in a minute cases where they thought he
was dead and he turned out to be alive and so on.
But it simply doesn't sound that way. It sounds like that he's
the presumption is he is alive. But nevertheless שמואל Shmuel reads it
as a case that no no no we've heard that he died.
Okay. So let's take a and therefore it's a case of a
widow being supported. So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says
like this: תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. מי שהלך למדינת
הים, Mi she-halach l'medinat hayam, somebody went overseas, ואשתו תובעת מזונות, v'ishto
tova'at mezonot,
his wife is demanding food. בני כהנים גדולים אומרים, Bnei kohanim gedolim
omrim, so this is a ברייתא braita which is a version of
our משנה. mishnah. The sons of the high priest say תשבע, tishava,
let her make an oath. חנן אומר לא תשבע, Chanan omer lo
tishava, חנן Chanan says do not make an oath. Okay. ואם בא
ואמר פסקתי לה מזונות נאמן. V'im ba v'amar pasakti lah mezonot ne'eman.
So even though she's allowed to collect without an oath, if he
comes and says no no no I've already made an arrangement then
he's believed. Now of course that's a little bit funny, like when
is he saying this? If he's showed up and said he made
an
arrangement then stop paying her now. Like it seems like he wasn't
around. So okay we'll talk about that in a minute but basically
what's clear is that he showed up. Okay. And before he showed
up okay anyway let's first look at רש"י Rashi what that means
he's נאמן. ne'eman. רש"י Rashi says: ואם בא ואמר פסקתי לה מזונות,
v'im ba v'amar pasakti lah mezonot, says רש"י: Rashi: אף תפסה צרורי,
af tafsa tzerori,
I had set up a bank account for her. So basically according
to רש"י Rashi what had happened was is we followed חנן, Chanan,
we sold off some property and then he came back and he
said what did you do? You sold off my property? What are
you talking about? I had set up a bank account for her.
So נאמן ne'eman he's believed ובשבועה ומחזרת מה שנתנו לה בית דין.
u'vshvu'ah u'machzeret mah she-natna lah beis din.
So רש"י's Rashi trying to figure this out, right? He showed up
but he showed up after we gave her the money. So what
does it mean he's believed? Believed means she'd have to pay the
money back. Okay. But now she has to pay the money back.
I mean why is he automatically believed? Like now she's she's got
the money in her pocket he's trying to take money away. So
נאמן ne'eman he's believed ובשבועה uvishvuah ומחזיר מה שנתנה לבית דין. umachazir
mah shenatna l'Beis Din. So Rashi's trying to figure this out, right?
He showed up, but he showed up after we gave the money.
So what does it mean he's believed? Believed didn't mean she'd have
to pay the money back? Okay, but now she has to pay
the money back. Why is he automatically believed? Now she's got the
money in her pocket, he's trying to take the money away from
her. Where is that presumption that he's telling the truth? So Rashi
has to balance it off by saying he's making a שבועה. shvuah.
Okay, so it's very complicated, right? Because it says, if he comes
and says, sounds like he's saying it now, but if she's saying
it now then anyway, so it has to be that he said
it after we did it, but then why is he נאמן? ne'eman?
So Rashi introduces a שבועה. shvuah.
Okay. We shouldn't be able to simply point to the bank account.
See look, look at the money I gave her before. I know,
that's the funny thing. Yeah, but I mean again, it's not I'm
giving a contemporary example of a bank account. He could just say,
I put some money in a box for her. How you going
to prove it, right?
Okay, the box... the box isn't there, it's empty. He says of
course it's empty, she emptied it out and then you know but
I set it aside for her.
Okay, so that's why Rashi introduces the שבועה. shvuah. Right.
So we have to, so anyway, so according to Rashi, it's hard
to understand exactly what kind he's showing up. Rashi has him showing
up afterwards, and then of course how could you just say נאמן,
ne'eman, so Rashi throws in the שבועה. shvuah. But what's clear though
is, is that the original selling off of his property was when
he was alive and overseas. So again that's a proof that we
will sell off property to provide for a wife if the husband
isn't around. Says the גמרא, Gemara, הכא נמי בששמעו בו שמת. hacha
nami b'sheshamu bo shemeis.
No, no, no, it's the same case, we thought he was dead.
Says the גמרא, Gemara, והא אם בא ואמר כמה. v'ha im ba
v'amar kama.
How could he have died? He came and he said, he showed
up. Says the גמרא, Gemara, אם בא אחר שמועה, im ba acher
shemuah, sure. It's like, you know, what who was it, Mark Twain?
Right, rumors of my of my demise have been greatly exaggerated. Okay,
we heard that he died, didn't literally mean he died, okay? So
therefore he but we sold off his property because we were supporting
the widow, that we'll do, and then it turned out all along
that he was alive. Okay, of course according to Shmuel then it's
pretty funny because according to well, whatever, according to Shmuel you understand
the נאמן ne'eman idea more without the whole idea of a שבועה,
shvuah, because according to Shmuel if he was alive, we shouldn't have
sold off the property to begin with, right? So now you understand
the end of the ברייתא beraisa a little bit better, right? It
turned out he was alive, oh we were only selling off the
property because we thought you were dead. Turns out you were alive,
we shouldn't have been selling off the property altogether, so you say
that you had set aside money for her, we'll believe you. Alright,
so let's take a look.
By the way take a look at תוספות. Tosafos.
תוספות Tosafos says like this, ואם בא ואמר פסקתי לה
מזונות,
v'im ba v'amar pasakti la
mezonos,
תוספות Tosafos says, פירש רש"י אף להוציא מידה מה שנתנו לה בית
דין בשבועה, perash Rashi af l'hotzi miyadah mah shenatnu lah Beis Din
b'shvuah, דאחזקתה נשפכה. d'achmasmadah nishpaka. Right, and והטעם דסתמא דאינש משקיש לה
צרורי, v'ha Ta'am d'stama d'nosh meshakish lah tzerorei,
we assume again that he would have put aside money, הלכך מוציא
מידה בשבועה. hilkach motzi miyadah b'shvuah. Of course we don't really assume
it according to Rav but whatever, somehow now that he's here and
he's saying it, we'll be willing to assume it. Okay, but that's
what Rashi says, that we'll believe him in order to now give
she has to give the money back. But the Ri gives another
explanation, ונראה לרבי דנאמן להטריחה שבועה ובשבועה תגבה מה שלותה ואכלה. v'nireh
l'Rabbi d'ne'eman l'hatrichah shvuah uvishvuah tigveh mah shelavsa v'achla.
And so תוספות Tosafos says no, no, no, what it means we
believe him is we believe him enough to insist that she make
a שבועה. shvuah. Okay, so basically she said, I need you to
give me food, we went ahead and sold like חנן, Chanan, we
didn't make her make a שבועה shvuah because we פוסקים pasken like
חנן, Chanan, we sold off the property and we went ahead or
she borrowed money and went ahead and she bought food. Now he
comes back and says, what are you doing? I had set aside
money for her. So according to Rashi we'll say okay, give it
back, he'll make a שבועה shvuah and give it back, but according
to תוספות Tosafos we'll say okay, well now you have to make
a שבועה shvuah to him, you know,
we're not going to make you give it back, we assumed that
he did not set aside the money, but now that he's making
this claim you have to make a שבועה shvuah to him that
that's not what happened. Okay, so it's a bit of an vague
exactly how we deal with it when he comes back. Alright, back
to the גמרא Gemara though. But anyway you have a case where
it sounds all of these cases sound very strongly like we will
support her in his absence, and the גמרא Gemara makes all of
them cases where we heard that he has died.
Okay, so
let's take a look.
Let's take a look.
תא שמע Ta shema come in here.
מי שהלך למדינת הים ואשתו תובעת מזונות. mi shehalach limdinas hayam v'ishto
tve'as mezonos. Guy went overseas, his wife is demanding to
be taken care of.
I know.
Now they take out the vov. אם בא ואמר צאי מעשה ידיך
במזונותייך, im ba v'amar tzei imas yadech b'mezonosayich, if he shows up
and says provide for yourself with your own labor, רשאי, rashai, he's
permitted. Again, if he's showed up and he said it, why do
we need בית דין Beis Din and where is he in
מדינת הים? medinas hayam? When is he showing up and saying? Again,
תוספות Tosafos tries to explain that the scenario is something like she
borrowed money in order to put food on the table and now
the creditors want to be paid back and he basically says to
them, well she had no right to borrow money from you, you
don't come to me for the money because I had told her
that she should just have provided for herself. Okay, so again, it's
a little bit complicated what's happening now, it seems like an after
the fact and he's making that claim.
But didn't she have a right to take out a loan? Doesn't
she have a right to take out a loan at any point
for any reason? Forget about that. So the creditors are coming thing,
but I mean she could have taken out money...
Yeah, but if she took out a loan to pay off his
debt then the
creditor... So he's basically saying that was not a loan on my
behalf, I had already made an arrangement with her. Okay, so that's
the one way of reading this, okay? That now basically if he
says that he's believed, again, question: why's he סתם stam believed if
fundamentally we would basically believe her? All right.
So anyway he's נאמן. ne'eman. רש"י: Rashi: קיבלו בית דין ופסקו. Kibeilu
Beis Din upasqu. Now בית דין Beis Din went ahead and he
did not say this and she didn't borrow money, they basically just
took his property, מה שפסקו פסקו. ma shepasqu pasqu. So that's fine,
if they decide to take his property before anything else happens, that's
also legitimate. So again, the wife wants to be fed, בית דין
Beis Din can come and take his property. So you see again,
the בית דין Beis Din has the right to do that if
he's not around. So Shmuel says הכא נמי בששמעו בו שמת. hacha
nami besheshmu bo shemeis. All right, that would be another special case
where they thought he was dead. Again, very, very weak answers of
Shmuel. All of these cases sound very much like בית דין Beis
Din will provide, but Shmuel explains all of them that they heard
he's dead. I will also point out that the two explanations given
to Shmuel about why we assume arrangements were made were already stated
in these two ברייתות. braisos. Right, this ברייתא braisa says צאי מעשה
ידיך במזונותיך. tzei ma'aseh yadecha bimzonosayich. So that acknowledges that that's one
scenario he could have provided for her. And the previous ברייתא braisa
says אם בא ואמר פסקתי
למזונות, im ba ve'amar pasakti lamazone, which basically means I set aside
money. So these two ברייתות braisos deal with him making claims of
the possible other arrangements he could have made. So you can understand
how Shmuel could have looked at these two ברייתות braisos and said,
"Look, there'd be these possible other arrangements he could have made, the
ברייתות braisos acknowledge them, once those are real possibilities, why do we
just סתם stam believe her? Why aren't we concerned that this is
what actually happened?" But again, the simple sense of the ברייתא braisa
is no, we do fundamentally believe her. If he makes a claim
that there was one of those other arrangements, then we'll have to
deal with it, okay, if he shows up alive and makes that
claim. But otherwise, we will basically follow her lead. Okay, so that's
the simple sense of these ברייתות. braisos. Shmuel's explaining that all these
cases are where we assume that he was dead. Yes.
מה שפסקו פסקו, ma shepasqu pasqu, those properties that are משועבדים, sha'ubidim,
meaning that someone, a third person comes and says you owe me
money in a loan from five years ago, they can take that
property from the לוקח loke'ach that was sold by בית דין? Beis
Din?
Yeah, I mean, that would always be true.
This is a regular case of a sale that
there was a lean on, right. Yeah, yeah, that wouldn't affect that.
Okay. תא שמע, Tashma, come and hear. מי שהלך למדינת הים ואשתו
תובעת מזונות. mishahalach limdinas hayam ve'ishto tova'as mzonos. Again,
somebody's gone overseas, his wife is demanding food. בית דין יורדין לנכסיו
וזנין ומפרנסין לאשתו. beis din yordin linchasav vezonin umfarnisin l'ishto. בית דין
Beis Din goes to his property
and sells it off to support his wife, אבל לא בניו ובנותיו,
aval lo banav uvenosav, not his sons and daughters. Why?
We already had that,
because a person does not have a legal obligation to provide the
food for his sons and daughters ולא דבר אחר, velo davar acher,
and not for anything else. We'll see what the anything else is.
Now, the reason this is a very powerful proof is you cannot
say it's בששמעו בו שמת. besheshmu bo shemeis. Why can you not
say we're assuming he's dead? Because if we're presuming a person is
dead, then what's the story about the sons and the daughters? Right,
they inherit, the sons inherit, and the daughters have a right to
be supported by the estate. So clearly, this is a case that
we're assuming he's alive, and all we're doing is we're exacting the
legal obligations that exist when a person is alive, which is to
provide for his wife מזונות. mzonos. And there you see that we
are providing for his wife's מזונות, mzonos, we're presuming he's
alive, okay, and we will do this if he's not around. And
that's why we're not providing for the kids. So אמר רב ששת
במשלשי את אשתו בידי שליש. Amar Rav Sheshes bemashlish es ishto bidei
shalis. Okay, no, no, this is a case where we know that
he had appointed somebody, he had made a trust essentially, and he
appointed somebody to write out checks and to provide the food bills
for his wife. So meaning whatever our concerns were, we had concerns,
the only reason, yes, you're right, I have to concede this is
a case where we're assuming he's alive, but Shmuel says we do
not sell off his estate because we assume he made an arrangement.
The arrangement was either he said to her provide for yourself, or
the arrangement was he set aside some money in a box somewhere.
But here we know he made an arrangement. The arrangement was he
said to a third person, "You know what, I want to go
ahead and I'm giving you control over my bank account, write out
checks to my wife." So that's the arrangement. We know there's an
arrangement. Now this third person comes along and he says, "You know
what, I also have to go למדינת הים. limdinas hayam. Goodbye, I'm
out of here, I'm done." Or the money was all spent, there's
nothing left in the bank account. So now Shmuel says now we're
entitled to sell off his estate, because now we don't have to
be concerned there was another arrangement around. We know what that other
arrangement was, and we know that that's no longer in force. Okay,
so Shmuel said you made a good point, you proved, all right,
I don't know, you made a good point, you proved that this
case was where he's presumed to be alive, but the reason that
therefore we can sell off his estate and we don't have to
be concerned about another arrangement is because we know what that other
arrangement was and we know that that's... it's no longer in force
and that's why now we're going to sell off his estate to
provide for his wife.
It's a good point. Like idiots. Yeah, I don't...
משריפי טבי? Mashrapi Tobo?
Whatever, something like that. משריפי... משריפי טבי? Mesharfei... Mesharfei Tova?
משריפי... Meshrapei... it's
a
strange idiom. I don't know, it's a good point. Yeah, I know.
I don't know how they translate the word משרא mashrei there in
your English. Anybody?
Usually means to soak cloth and dye. What? Usually
means to soak something... משריפי טבי? Mashrapei Tova?
משריפי... Meshrapei... He just said appointed to provide for, I don't know.
משריפי טבי. Meshrapei Tova.
Yeah, well that's the... yeah, I don't know what... okay anyway. אי
הכי Ei hachi says the גמרא, Gemara, if that's true,
maybe it's משרא לצררה, mashra l'tzarara, I don't know.
משרא? mashra? I don't know, that's what...
it says שגמל she'gamal לא היה נותן לה כסף במישרים. lo hayah
noten lah kesef be'meisharim. מישרים, meisharim, like directly? משרא mashra like ישר,
yashar, direct? All right,
anyway.
Fine. All right, fine.
We'll look it up...
משראי דשדי אדי דשליש. mashraei deshadi adei deshlish. אי הכי, Ei hachi,
בנו ובנותיו נמי, benov u'venotav nami, if that's true, why not provide
for his sons and daughters? Okay, because presumably he's made arrangements that
would have included his sons and daughters. So the גמרא Gemara says,
כשהשליש לזו ולא השליש לזו, kesheshlish lezu velo hishlish lezu, no, he
only made arrangements for his wife, not his sons and daughters. So
if he had made for sons and daughters, then in the bank
account that emptied out, we would have presumed that he would want
to continue supporting them even though he has no legal obligation. That's
true. But we would have continued supporting them because he had indicated
he wants to. But the scenario was, was that he did not
make arrangements for his sons and daughters, he only made arrangements for
his wife, and therefore we're only going to continue to support her
because that is his legal obligation. גמרא Gemara says מאי פסקה? mai
piska? What makes you split between the two? Why should we assume
he provided for his wife and not his sons and daughters? And
תוספות Tosafot says what type of crazy question is that? The whole
point is that he has a legal obligation to his wife and
he doesn't have a legal obligation to his sons and daughters. So
it's very reasonable to assume that he set up a fund for
his wife for what his legal obligation was and not for his
sons and daughters. But maybe the גמרא Gemara understands no, it's one
thing to say he doesn't have a legal obligation, but if the
guy went so far to make arrangements, then presumably he would not
have abandoned his family. אלא אמר רב פפא, Ela amar Rav Papa,
so rather says רב פפא, Rav Papa, כששמע בו שמת בעד אחד.
kesheshama bo shemet be'ed echad. Now this is going to be very
creative, okay? Yes, we heard he's dead. Now if we heard he's
dead, the question of course is then why not provide for the
sons and daughters? Because we only heard he's dead through one witness.
Okay, this is getting us back to יבמות Yevamot stories. דאי בעיא
אינסובי בעד אחד שריא, de'i be'ya i'nasuvei be'ed echad sharya, as we
know from יבמות, Yevamot, she can get remarried by the testimony of
one witness. מצי מנסבא, matzi minasva, she can marry if she wishes.
מזוני נמי יהבינן לה, mezonei nami yahavinan lah, so the wife we
say is allowed to assume that her husband is dead. Since she's
allowed to assume that her husband is dead, she can be supported
by the estate as a widow.
בנו ובנותיו דאי בעו למיחת לנכסיה בעד אחד לא מצי נחתי, benov
u'venotav de'i ba'u lemeichat lenichsei be'ed echad lo matzi nachteis, they cannot
take seize the estate, they cannot, you know, be collect as heirs
by עד אחד. ed echad. There's no special believability of an עד
אחד ed echad for heirs to believe that their father is dead.
There's only a special thing for the wife to allowed to remarry.
So for them, one עד ed is not enough evidence that their
father is dead. In that case, מזוני נמי לא יהבינן להו, mezonei
nami lo yahavinan lehu, so we also don't provide for them. So
from their perspective their father is alive and from her perspective her
husband is dead. And that's the difference. But again, we are only
going to provide for her because we assume that the husband is
dead, not when we assume he's alive.
ומי איתא דפסקינן לה מזוני ויורשיהם לא מנחתינן להו יתומים. U'mi ita
d'paskinan lah mezonei veyorsheihem lo manchatinan lehu yetomim. רש"י Rashi says אינהם
אינם
מניחים...
einam
einam manichim...
There you go.
There you go. Yep. That's surprising because if I recall from יבמות,
Yevamot, we allow her to marry with the עד אחד ed echad
because if she's willing to take that step, then we're going to
assume she's really sure. Right. But to take the money she doesn't
have to be so sure.
Yeah, that's a good point. You know, that's a good point, that
if the believability of the עד אחד ed echad is, right, is
all because about the way the גמרא Gemara explains it, like she,
you know, she's risking all of those consequences and that makes sure
that she's being doubly sure, yeah, what's she risking here? That's a
good point. But let's also not forget that even if the husband
just were alive and not around, he would have an obligation, right?
So it's really just addressing שמואל's Shmuel concern that there had been
some other arrangement. But you make a good point. Like, would we
allow her to collect the כתובה, ketubah, the full lump sum כתובה
ketubah payment by the עד אחד? ed echad? That would be maybe
not. Maybe here, since even had the husband alive she'd be entitled
to be supported, yes. Bobby had a question.
If the wife died, does the husband have
an
obligation to support the children immediately? Well, yes. One of the כתובה
ketubah obligations that he makes is that is to ensure that, I
mean, it's the כתובת בנין דכרין ketubat benin dikhrin and... I mean,
one of the כתובה ketubah obligations he makes... is to make sure
that he continues to support her daughters, you know, until they basically
get married off. And the sons are basically seen as being able
to be provided for because they're going to inherit the father's property
eventually.
Yeah, yeah, I'm just starting to think about about what happens if,
I
mean,
just because she's dead he does not have more of an ongoing
obligation.
No, the obligation to support the daughters is when he dies. When
he dies, she's supported by the estate and the daughters are supported
as well until they basically get married off.
But if she dies, then his obligations don't change from when she
was alive, you know, I mean that's the funny thing is that
he doesn't have a legal obligation to provide for his kids we
just assume that he would
take care of his own children. Right, when he's alive he's not
obligated.
Yeah, that's the funny thing.
It doesn't make sense that you can have children and not be
responsible, as a male provide and not be responsible for that.
Yeah, I mean that's the thing that the גמרא Gemara has it
up over six.
Right,
I was going to say, I was going to say, at very
young age, right, up through like the age of like five or
six or whatever he is obligated, but beyond that, not, you know,
because then they should be out getting jobs already.
They should be out getting jobs already. I think that's all, I
mean that really would be what happened, kids would apprentice themselves at
extremely young ages, yes.
There is an obligation to teach your son תורה Torah and to
teach your son a
trade, right, not to actually feed them.
Right, yeah, if
there's only
one witness to the death and the sons don't inherit yet.
Yeah, that's what we're saying. Yeah, yeah, very interesting situation.
Yeah, they have
no evidence that the father is dead so they can't yet take
the property, they can't inherit.
Right, so what happens, it just stays that way as long as,
let's say he went on a trip and only one person...
Yeah, until they get enough, well תוספות Tosafot discusses like, you know,
I mean right, at what type of, yeah, what type of evidence
you would need under what circumstances, but yeah, I mean, you know,
it's establishing death. Right. Okay, so let's take a look now, but
yes, but that is true that a person does not have an
obligation to support his kids beyond like the very once they get
to be like the age of around five or six or so.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
All right, מאי דבר אחר, Mai davar acher, what is this other
thing that we don't provide her with? רב חסדא אמר תכשיט, Rav
Chisda amar tachshit,
we don't provide her with like jewelry or רש״י Rashi says perfume.
We only provide her with the basic obligations when the husband is
not around. רב יוסף אמר צדקה, Rav Yosef amar tzedakah, we don't
have a like if everybody in the community is being asked to
make a צדקה tzedakah contribution,
we don't do that, we don't take that from his property if
he's not around assuming like, you know, even if everybody is doing
it as long as it's somewhat volitional then we do not take
that from his property. מן דאמר תכשיט, Man de’amar tachshit, the one
that says we do not use the money to spend it for
a
תכשיט, tachshit, כל שכן צדקה, kol sheken tzedakah, certainly צדקה tzedakah not,
because that's not even for his own wife. מן דאמר צדקה, Man
de’amar tzedakah, the one that says that we do not use the
property for צדקה tzedakah purposes, אבל תכשיט יהבינן לה, aval tachshit yahavinan
lah,
we would use some money to allow her to get some jewelry
or perfume דלא ניחא ליה דתתגנא ודתנוול, de’lo nicha leh detitgana v’detinval,
he would not want his wife to go around looking disgusting just
because he's not around. So some basic things even if they're not
the most basic issues
about food, but just general how she like is able to take
care of herself would also be included.
רש״י Rashi says בשמים besamim here. Yeah, תכשיט, tachshit, בשמים, besamim, ליד
le-yad
כ״ט kaf tet עמוד ב׳. amud bet. Second line of the עמוד
ב׳, amud bet, sorry.
תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. היבמה, Hayevamah, ג׳ gimel חדשים
הראשונים, chadashim harishonim, sister-in-law
for the first three months, ניזונת משל בעלה, nizonet mishel ba’alah,
is supported by her dead husband's estate because during those three months
she cannot yet do יבום yibbum because maybe she's pregnant. Okay. מכאן
ואילך, Mikan ve’eylach, from that point on where it's now the brother-in-law's
obligation to do יבום, yibbum, אינה ניזונת לא משל בעלה ולא משל
יבם. eina nizonet lo mishel ba’alah v’lo mishel yavam.
So she gets neither because she's basically no longer considered a normal
widow would continue to be supported, but because she's supposed to be
married off to the brother-in-law, it's like you know it's sort of
a widow stops being supported when she marries somebody else. So here
she's sort of caught in this middle
stage and so she's no longer because the מצוה mitzvah of יבום
yibbum is supposed to happen, she's no longer supported from her dead
husband's estate. But because it hasn't happened yet, she's not supported from
the brother-in-law's estate, which is not very fair to her. So now
it goes on and says the following. עמדה בדין וברח, Amda badin
u-varach,
now there was a court case basically where she said to the
guy
to the brother-in-law, right, basically you know make up your mind buddy,
do יבום yibbum or do חליצה, chalitzah, one or the other, so
that either I'll be part of you know married to you and
you'll support me or I'll be freed from you and I'll go
back to being supported by my dead husband's estate. So עמדה בדין
וברח, amda badin u-varach, and then he went ahead and he ran
away.
Now there's an interesting question, is it specifically because of ברח barach
ברח barach that he is you know, evading judgment, or is it
because once it's עמד בדין, amad bedin, once he's sort of has
to act on it, then even if he it's not he's not
doing anything wrong, he's just sick, or he's postponed, or whatever it
might be, but now he basically is his inaction, whether it's his
fault or not, is keeping her essentially as a type of an
עגונה. agunah. It's keeping her with, you know, within this middle state.
So, once the basically court has come to him and said buddy,
you know, you gotta do something, then he is responsible for providing
for her until that situation resolves itself. Okay, that's one way of
understanding it. The other is specifically because of ברח, barach, specifically because
he's evading his responsibilities. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, so
anyway, what do you see? You see though, that even though that
if he's not physically around, he has to provide for her. So
how, isn't this similar to the husband not being physically around and
בית דין Beis Din going ahead and providing? Now obviously there's a
big difference. So which, this is an easy question. This is a
softball. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר ליה שמואל, amla leih Shmuel, Shmuel tells to you, למה ניחוש
לה? lemai neichush lah? No, in that case obviously he's not satisfying
his obligations to her. There's nothing to be concerned about. What should
we be concerned about? למה ניחוש לה להאי, lemai neichush lah lehai,
in this case. אי משום צררי, ie mishum tzrari, maybe he set
aside money for her? לא מיקרבא דעתיה לגבה. lo mikrav daiteih legabah.
He doesn't, he's no longer he doesn't feel close to her. He
doesn't you know, they've never been they haven't been married, he just
has this מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibbum. Besides which he ran away.
So anyway, why should we assume that he set aside money? אי
משום מעשה ידיה, ie mishum maaseh yadeha, and if it's because he's
basically saying well, you know, maybe she can now earn and put
food on her own table because of her own earnings. So no,
לא משתעבדא ליה. lo mishtabda lei. She has no responsibility to him
for that, which is interesting because it means he might be in
a case where he's obligated to support her before they're married, but
she is not yet obligated to work for him, that her מעשה
ידיה maaseh yadeha go to him, right? In this sort of middle
state. Which is interesting, which means that she's entitled to keep her
own מעשה ידיה, maaseh yadeha, okay, because right, but he is still
providing obligated to support her. So in that middle state where because
they're not yet married her work doesn't go to him, but because
he has to do something about it, you know, he has to
make sure that she's provided for, so therefore there's no arrangement that
we assume was made and therefore or could have been made and
therefore we would make sure that we would take from his estate
to pay for her. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues says
the
following: יבם's yabam estate.
יבם's yabam estate. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. האישה שהלכה היא ובעלה למדינת
הים, ha'isha shehalcha hi uvaalah limdinas hayam, she and her husband went
to
מדינת הים, medinas hayam, ובאה ואמרה מת בעלי, uvaasah veamrah meish baali,
my husband died. So she's believed. רצתה מזונות, ratzah nizonos, if she
wants to be supported by the estate, that's what you do for
an אלמנה, almanah, or רצתה תגבה כתובתה, ratzah tigveh kesuvatah, or collect
her כתובה. kesuvah. הא אם אמרה גרשני בעלי,
ha
im
teish geirashani baali, my husband divorced me,
then in that case מתפרנסת והולכת עד כדי כתובתה. mitparneset veholechet ad
kedei kesuvatah. She is supported until the כתובה kesuvah runs out. What
does that mean? It means that a woman for whatever reason, and
I won't go into it right now, is believed when she says
her husband died but not when she says her husband divorced her.
So we don't really believe her when she says her husband divorced
her. But she's saying he divorced me and I demand my כתובה.
kesuvah. So we'll say look, here's what we're going ahead and do.
We will pay your food bill because ממה נפשך, mi'man nafshach, either
you're still married and he has to give you מזונות, mezonot, or
you're not married and you're entitled to your כתובה. kesuvah. So we
will pay out your food bill until the value of your כתובה,
kesuvah, okay, and at that point we're gonna stop because maybe you're
divorced and you're not entitled to more. But we're not gonna give
you a lump sum payment of your כתובה kesuvah because maybe your
husband's alive and you're still married. So the גמרא Gemara says you
see that, what do you see? You see though, we are going
willing to pay out the food bill even though the husband isn't
around. Okay, גמרא Gemara says הכא נמי דשמעו בו
שמת. hacha nami deshamu bo shemeis. Oh no, that case where she
says he divorced me, we heard that he had died. Okay, of
course if we heard that he had died, why is she bothered
saying he divorced her? So the גמרא Gemara says ומאי שנא עד
כדי כתובתה, umai shna ad kedei kesuvatah, and then why is it
so saying until the value of the כתובה, kesuvah, if he had
died she's an אלמנה almanah and she can get supported indefinitely. היא
היא דאפסדה אנפשה, hi hi de'afsada anafsha, cause she hurt herself. Meaning
the חידוש chidush is is that she if she had said nothing
we would have continued to support her assuming that she was an
אלמנה. almanah. Because she says that she was a גרושה, grushah, now
we're only gonna stop we're gonna stop supporting her once it hits
the value of the כתובה. kesuvah.
Better never to say גרשני geirashani then.
Well at least not from this monetary perspective in this particular scenario.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, תא שמע, ta shema,
come and hear, כיצד אמרו ממאנת אין לה מזונות. keitzad amru mima'enet
ein lah mezonot. In what scenario did they say a ממאנת, mima'enet,
a girl who refuses the husband that her brother or mother's married
her off to, right this minor girl, so she doesn't get מזונות
mezonot because you know she's not married when she does מיאון. me'un.
What's the scenario?
Where I lost my place. Okay. אי אתה יכול לומר ביושבת תחת
בעלה. I Atah Yachol Lomeir B'Yoshevet Tachat Ba'alah. It can't be a
case where they're still together and she hasn't done מיאון miun yet,
okay, because in that case, שהרי בעלה חייב במזונותיה, she-harei ba'alah chayav
b'mezonoteha, because as long as they're together, the husband has to support
her. אלא כגון שהלך
למדינת הים,
Ella, k'gon she-halach
l'medinat hayam, so he went overseas. לוותה ואכלה, Latah v'achalah, now she
borrowed money in order to put food on the table, and עמדה
ומיאנה, v'amdah u'mi'anah, and then she did מיאון. miun. And now what
do we say? We say you did מיאון, miun, here's the חידוש,
chiddush, because obviously it's not just saying from this point on you're
not married, that's not a חידוש, chiddush, of course this point on
you're not married, no מזונות. mezonot. We say retroactively you were never
married. Okay, now, if he had actually paid for her מזונות, mezonot,
we don't say after she does מיאון, miun, fine, you want to
do מיאון, miun, fine, go pay me ten years of back food
payment. Okay, then it would make מיאון miun not feasible. But in
this case, it's not paying him back the money; she had borrowed
the money to put the מזונות mezonot on the table, and now
we said now that you've done מיאון, miun, you're not in a
position to collect that money from your ex-husband, okay, because now retroactively
you weren't married, and now we'll say you have to pay back
that loan, okay? So, he's not entitled to tell you, 'Give me
all the money I paid you for the food bills over the
last ten years.' But in the case where you borrowed money...
she borrowed money, mind you, she's a minor, how did she borrow
money?
Yeah, so, you know, so there are cases basically, this whole age
of פעוטות pe'utot where girl... where somebody who's like, you know, although
still a minor, enough... well no, but there's rabbinic קניינים kinyanim that
minors can do if they're of, you know, if they're like 10,
11 years old, I mean, you know, פעוטות pe'utot might even be
younger, 7 or 8 or whatever. But yeah, you're right, there would
be cases where there's a rabbinic age... there's an age where rabbinically
we let them engage in certain transactions, right, even though, you know,
whatever, even though they're minors, as long as
they know how to take care...
okay. So, or it could be that the parent, the mother did
it for her, I don't know, so that's a good question. So
it says, so you see, עמדה ומיאנה, amdah u'mi'anah, so in that
case she can't collect back from her husband. So the גמרא Gemara
says, טעמא דמיאנה, ta'ama d'mi'anah, the reason is that she did מיאון,
miun, she can't collect. הא לא מיאנה, ha lo mi'anah, if she
had not done מיאון, miun, יהבינן לה, yehavinan lah, we would give
her the money back that she had borrowed, even though she had
borrowed it when the husband was overseas, so again you see that
we're willing to provide for a person when the husband isn't around
or a wife. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר לך שמואל, amar
lach Shmuel, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, no, no, no, again
in this case, this is a special case. Of course we're going
to believe her in this case. What are we really being concerned
about? אי משום צרורי, ei mishum tzerorei, if it's setting aside money
for
her, לקטנה לא מסר, l'ktana lo masar, to a person, like we
said earlier, a man won't put aside money for his underage wife,
he won't be able to trust her with it.
Who's going to be... is he going to set aside the food?
I don't know. But if... that's what שמואל's Shmuel point is, is
here of course we're going to assume he didn't make arrangements because
of this. ואי משום מעשה ידיה, v'ei mishum ma'aseh yadeha, if it's
because he'll say, well maybe he had made arrangements that she should,
you know, earn for herself, לקטנה לא ספקא, l'ktana lo safka, as
a general rule, although we before it's possible that a minor could
earn enough money for food on the table, that's not generally going
to happen. So basically he said, 'Look, because it's a case of
a קטנה, ktana, we're going to assume that he did not really
make an arrangement. But if it was a case of an adult,
then we would assume there was be an arrangement and she would
not be entitled to, we would not go ahead and take his
property to pay for her food.' All right, so anyway, all the
evidence is against שמואל Shmuel but he has a way of explaining
everything. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי הוי עלה, mai hava alah,
what was the upshot? So כי אתא רב דימי, ki ata Rav
Dimi, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came, אמר, amar, he said, מעשה
בא לפני רבי בבית שערים, ma'aseh ba lifnei Rabbi b'Beit She'arim, we
mentioned רבי Rabbi and בית שערים Beit She'arim just a day or
two ago. Okay, so a case happened with רבי Rabbi in בית
שערים, Beit She'arim, ופסק לה מזונות, u'pasak lah mezonot, that a woman
whose husband had gone overseas and רבי Rabbi made, you know, had
the בית דין beis din go ahead and take property to feed
her. לפני רבי ישמעאל בציפורי, Lifnei Rabbi Yishmael b'Tzippori,
in front of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael in ציפורי, Tzippori, which is
where רבי Rabbi had moved from בית שערים Beit She'arim if you
remember, ולא פסק לה מזונות, v'lo pasak lah mezonot, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael refused to do it. תמה רבי יוחנן, Tamah Rabbi Yochanan, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was astounded. וכי מה ראה רבי ישמעאל שלא פסק
לה מזונות? V'chi mah ra'ah Rabbi Yishmael she-lo pasak lah mezonot? How
did רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael not provide for this poor woman whose
husband had gone overseas? הלא נחלקו בני כהנים גדולים וחנן, Halo nechelku
Bnei Kohanim Gedolim v'Chanan, in our משנה mishnah the only debate between
the בני כהנים גדולים Bnei Kohanim Gedolim and חנן, Chanan, אלא לענין
שבועה, ella l'inyan shvu'ah, was only when you take a שבועה. shvu'ah.
אבל מזוני יהבינן לה, Aval mezoni yehavinan lah,
but for מזונות mezonot everybody agrees you provide, right? That's the simple
sense of the משנה. mishnah. You provide for a woman whose husband
isn't around and the only question is when you take a שבועה.
shvu'ah. אמר ליה רב שמן בר אבא, Amar lei Rav Shemen bar
Abba, so רב שמן בר אבא Rav Shemen bar Abba said, כבר
תרגמה רבנו שמואל בבבל, Kvar tirgemah Rabbeinu Shmuel b'Bavel, ah,
here's how to get around that משנה, mishnah, our master שמואל—interesting, Shmuel
רבנו שמואל, Rabbeinu Shmuel, in the בבלי Bavli it's never רבנו שמואל—anyway,
Rabbeinu Shmuel already interpreted it in Babylonia, כששמעו בו שמת, k'she-shamu bo
she-meit, that the whole case in the משנה mishnah that we're providing
for her is where the husband is presumed dead. And he basically,
שמואל Shmuel basically takes the position that when the husband is assumed
to be alive, we don't provide for her, even though that's not
פשט pshat in the משנה. mishnah. He says our משנה mishnah is
talking about that he's presumed dead.
But didn't רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael say no מזונות mezonos because she
doesn't want to take a שבועה? shvuah? Or is the שבועה shvuah
afterward?
Well, I don't know, it sounds like, it doesn't sound like that,
it sounds like he threw the case out fundamentally, and also according
to חנן Chanan the שבועה shvuah is afterward, assuming you פסקן pasken
like חנן. Chanan.
Anyway, so he said look, look, look, שמואל's Shmuel got an answer
to the משנה. mishna. אמר ליה, Amar leh, wait, let's just hear
the answer. אמר ליה Amar leh רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said back,
פסטריתו בכולי האי? pastrisu bekulei hai? What, you know you went to
such a long, such a... you went on such a limb to
explain the משנה mishna away? Meaning, give me a break, that's not
the case of the משנה. mishna. So finally the גמרא Gemara voices
like an objection like come on, that's how far you're going to
go to do away with the evidence of the משנה? mishna? You
got a clear משנה mishna that says you provide for the wife,
the only question is when you take the שבועה, shvuah, and you're
going to make a whole תירוץ teretz and say the משנה mishna
is a special case that you assume that the husband is dead.
But what's... what'll we do other times? But maybe it's like, you
know again, there's so much evidence and you've got this poor woman
that needs מזונות, mezonos, so it's not a fair קנייטש knetch to
do on this woman's account.
And it's a solid
so to wonder about all these other possible cases. Right. So let's
take a look. The גמרא Gemara has an identical case. כי אתא
רבין, Ki ata Ravin, when רבין Ravin came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, אמר מעשה בא לפני רבי בבית שערים, amar maiseh ba lifnei
Rebbe be-Beit She'arim, he had the case but in the reverse. It
came to רבי Rebbe ולא פסק לה מזונות ve-lo pasak lah mezonos
and he did not,
basically right over מזונות mezonos for this woman, provide for her from
the estate. לפני רבי ישמעאל בציפורי, Lifnei Rabbi Yishmael be-Tzippori, it came
before רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael in ציפורי, Tzippori, ופסק לה מזונות ve-pasak
lah mezonos and he did give over the property from the estate
for מזונות. mezonos. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, so רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said, מה ראה רבי שלא פסק לה? mah ra'ah Rebbe
she-lo pasak lah? What did רבי Rebbe see not to provide for
this woman? דלא נחלקו חנן ובני כהנים גדולים אלא אשבועה. Dela nechlaku
Chanan ve-Bnei Kohanim Gedolim ela al shvuah. Where חנן Chanan and the
בני כהנים גדולים Bnei Kohanim Gedolim argued was regarding when you take
the oath. אבל מזונות יהבינן לה, Aval mezonos yahivnan lah, everyone agrees
that a woman whose husband isn't around you provide for her. אמר
רב שמן בר אבא, Amar Rav Shemen bar Abba, כבר תרגמה שמואל
באתרא דרבנו שמואל
שמואל. kvar targeimah Shmuel be-atras rabbenu Shmuel Shmuel. שמואל's Shmuel already dealt
with that משנה. mishna. He over-brought, he explained away that משנה. mishna.
כששמעו בו שמת. ksheshamu bo shemet.
Wait, let me hear that story again because
it's a question where who said which, whether רבי Rebbe said yes
and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said no or the reverse. כששמעו בו
שמת. ksheshamu bo shemet. שמואל Shmuel already explained away that משנה mishna
that it's the case where the husband is presumed dead. אמר ליה,
Amar leh, so he said back, פסטריתו בכולי האי? pastrisu bekulei hai?
What,
you're going to go that far of an extent to explain away
the משנה? mishna? Give me a break, of course that's not פשט.
pshat. Now the גמרא Gemara ends: והלכתא כוותיה דרב, ve-hilchesa kevasei de-Rav,
we rule like רב, Rav, which is clearly how the end of
this was, like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan or whatever, which is we
provide מזונות mezonos for a woman whose husband is away. Okay? And
we assume he did not make an arrangement and we provide מזונות
mezonos like the simple sense of the משנה. mishna. ופסקינן מזונות לאשת
איש, u-paskinan mezonos l-eshet ish,
and we provide מזונות mezonos for a married woman. Number one. Number
two, once we're talking about this we might, and we're getting to
the end of the מסכתא, masekhta, we might as well deal with
some unfinished business. So: והלכתא כוותיה דרב הונא, ve-hilchesa kevasei de-Rav Huna,
we also in this regard rule like רב הונא, Rav Huna, דאמר
רב הונא אמר רב, de-amar Rav Huna amar Rav, דאמר רב הונא
אמר רב: de-amar Rav Huna amar Rav: יכולה אשה שתאמר לבעלה איני
ניזונת ואיני עושה, yechola isha she-tomar le-ba'alah eini nizonet ve-eini osa,
very important conclusion, that the providing of מזונות mezonos in exchange for
the מעשי ידיים ma'aseh yadayim was done to protect her interests. So
therefore she is entitled to say to her husband unilaterally, "I don't
want, I will thank you very much, I've got a... I'm a
partner in a law firm, you can... I will keep my salary
check and you can go ahead and keep your מזונות." mezonos. Okay?
So she's entitled to say that to her husband, ultimately it is
to protect her interest. It's not just he's entitled to say it
to her, she's entitled to say it to him. והלכתא כוותיה דרב
זביד ve-hilchesa kevasei de-Rav Zvid
בקוניא, be-kunya, and I've no idea what this is doing other than
we're talking doing הלכתות hilchesas so the גמרא Gemara sometimes likes three
so we're going to do a third הלכתא. hilchesa. We rule like
רב זביד Rav Zvid regarding קוניא kunya which are certain types of
glazed pottery vessels. דאמר רב זביד, de-amar Rav Zvid, so רב זביד
Rav Zvid says there's a debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos
whether this is sort of glazed with a type of a metal
glaze or glazed with a glass glaze. רש"י Rashi says it's metal,
תוספות Tosafos says it's a glass. Okay? דאמר רב זביד הני מאני
דקוניא, de-amar Rav Zvid hanei mane de-kunya, these vessels of, these glazed
pottery vessels, חיורי ואוכמי, chivarei ve-uchmei, white and black ones, שרי, sharei,
are permissible, because they don't overly absorb. There's also the question here
are we talking about them being used with hot or used with
cold? It could be we're talking about that they were used to
store wine and they were only used with cold and the question
is how much will a vessel, a pottery vessel, absorb with cold
in a way that the wine won't be able to come back
out? You know, a סתם יינם stam yeinam type of a question,
wine of non-Jews. So white and black is not a problem. ירוקי
yerokei green, אסירי asiri is a problem, because those clearly have some
type of a... רש"י Rashi says אלום alum which is not aluminum,
I forget what אלום alum is.
It's a thing. Yeah. It's not aluminum. I forget, it's one... it's
a certain type of a metal, anyway, something is in the glass
or in the glaze that causes it to absorb and then the
taste can't come back out again, so you can't כשר kasher it.
Okay?
ואמריינו אלא דריש בי כרטופי, ve-amreinu ella de-reish bei kartufi, and even
the white and black that's okay, that's... Tell me if there are
no like ridges and cracks so there's no way for the taste
to get in, אבל אית בהו קרטופיי אסור, aval it beih kartufei
assur, and if it does have that, it's forbidden. The taste gets
in and it can't come out. This gets to all these questions
right about pottery and glaze and all these types of things. Interestingly
because תוספות Tosfos says it is talking about a glass glaze, I'll
turn you to תוספות Tosfos where תוספות Tosfos says like this. It
says here
chrome
or
potash.
Potash, okay.
He says like this. אבל בהתכת זכוכית, aval behataxas zechuchis,
if you see two lines down in the wide lines of תוספות,
Tosfos, he says when it comes to glazing with a type of
a glass glaze, ניחא דאפילו קוניא של זכוכית אינו נאסר. nicha de'afilu
konyah shel zechuchis einu ne'asar.
Nowadays if it was all of glass, it wouldn't be a problem
לפי שנתבשל היטב ואינו נבלע. lefi shenisbashel heiteiv ve'eino nivla.
Our glass which is like well processed and it's pure glass, right,
it would not absorb the taste. אבל קוניא, aval konyah, but this
אבל קוניא aval konyah ולא נתבשל כל כך velo nisbashel kol kach
and the glass was not well processed and it had these other
types of, you know, of metals in it and alloys or whatever,
you know,
impurities, ובלע טפי uvala tfei and it did absorb. But anyway, what
I wanted you to see is תוספות Tosfos says that glass doesn't
absorb. Unless it's this problematic type of a glass, okay? Question is,
does it only mean it doesn't absorb in cold, or even doesn't
absorb in hot? As you might be familiar, there's, you know, some
that feel that glass is never, can never, you can never כשר
kasher up glass, it doesn't absorb at all. There's a whole debate
about what the status of glass is in הלכה. halacha.
Okay, רש"י Rashi is correct, glass is completely non-porous except for rare
specialty glasses that are extremely expensive, never used in cooking.
But what about glass that's not processed well? Will that be porous
or is there such a thing?
It's the chemicals, it's the problem. The only thing is if there's
scratches in it, you can get stuff in the scratches.
Okay.